Politicians in a big, complex, sophisticated I.T. project? Oh, that's going to be a disaster waiting to happen. Not necessarily. There is a precedent for technology-enabled service that has been initiated by politicians in multiple countries and has been hugely successful: national lotteries. Let's take Britain as an example. Our government didn't design the national lottery, it didn't fund the national lottery, it doesn't operate the national lottery. It simply passed the National Lottery Act and this is what followed. This act defines what a national lottery will look like. It specifies certain benefits that the state can uniquely bestow on the operators. And it puts some obligations on those operators. In terms of spreading gambling activity to the masses, this was an unqualified success. But let's suppose that our aim is to bring new economic activity to the base of the pyramid. Could we use the same model? I believe we could. So imagine that policymakers outlined a facility. Let's call it national e-markets, NEMs for short. Think of it as a regulated public utility. So it's on a par with the water supply or the road network. And it's a series of markets for low-level trade that can be fulfilled by a person or a small company. And government has certain benefits it can uniquely bestow on these markets. It's about public spending going through these markets to buy public services at the local level. It's about interfacing these markets direct into the highest official channels in the land. It's about enshrining government's role as a publicist for these markets. It's about deregulating some sectors so that local people can enter them. So, taxi journeys might be one example. And there are certain obligations that should go with those benefits to be placed on the operators, and the key one is, of course, that the operators pay for everything, including all the interfacing into the public sector. So imagine that the operators make their return by building a percentage markup into each transaction. Imagine that there's a concession period defined of maybe 15 years in which they can take all these benefits and run with them. And imagine that the consortia who bid to run it are told, whoever comes in at the lowest percentage markup on each transaction to fund the whole thing will get the deal. So government then exits the frame. This is now in the hands of the consortium. Either they are going to unlock an awful lot of economic opportunity and make a percentage on all of it or it's all going to crash and burn, which is tough on their shareholders. It doesn't bother the taxpayer necessarily. And there would be no constraints on alternative markets. So this would just be one more choice among millions of Internet forums. But it could be very different, because having access to those state-backed facilities could incentivize this consortium to seriously invest in the service. Because they would have to get a lot of these small transactions going to start making their return. So we're talking about sectors like home hair care, the hire of toys, farm work, hire of clothes even, meals delivered to your door, services for tourists, home care. This would be a world of very small trades, but very well-informed, because national e-markets will deliver data. So this is a local person potentially deciding whether to enter the babysitting market. And they might be aware that they would have to fund vetting and training if they wanted to go into that market. They'd have to do assessment interviews with local parents who wanted a pool of babysitters. Is it worth their while? Should they be looking at other sectors? Should they be moving to another part of the country where there's a shortage of babysitters? This kind of data can become routine. And this data can be used by investors. So if there's a problem with a shortage of babysitters in some parts of the country and the problem is nobody can afford the vetting and training, an investor can pay for it and the system will tithe back the enhanced earnings of the individuals for maybe the next two years. This is a world of atomized capitalism. So it's small trades by small people, but it's very informed, safe, convenient, low-overhead and immediate. Some rough research suggests this could unlock around 100 million pounds' worth a day of new economic activity in a country the size of the U.K. Does that sound improbable to you? That's what a lot of people said about turbo trading in financial exchanges 20 years ago. Do not underestimate the transformative power of truly modern markets. Thank you. (Applause)
¿Los políticos en un gran proyecto informático complejo y sofisticado? Eso es un desastre en potencia. No necesariamente. Hay un precedente de servicios con componente tecnológica iniciado por políticos en varios países y que ha sido muy exitoso: las loterías nacionales. Analicemos el caso de Gran Bretaña. Nuestro gobierno no diseñó la lotería nacional no fundó la lotería nacional, ni opera la lotería nacional. Votó la Ley de la Lotería Nacional y esto es lo que ocurrió. Esta ley define las características de una lotería nacional. Especifica ciertos beneficios que sólo el Estado puede otorgar a los operadores. E impone algunas obligaciones a esos operadores. En materia de difusión del juego de azar entre las masas tuvo un éxito sin parangón. Pero supongamos que nuestro objetivo es brindar nueva actividad económica a la base de la pirámide. ¿Podríamos usar el mismo modelo? Creo que sí. Imaginen que los políticos definen una estructura. Llamémosla Mercados Electrónicos Nacionales, o MEN. Piénsenlo como un servicio público regulado. Está a la par del suministro de agua o la red de carreteras. Y hay una serie de mercados bajo nivel de intercambio que puede ser atendido por una persona o una pequeña empresa. Y el gobierno cuenta con ciertos beneficios que puede otorgar a estos mercados. Es gasto público destinado a estos mercados para comprar servicios públicos a nivel local. Se trata de interconectar estos mercados directamente con los más altos canales oficiales. Se trata de consagrar el papel del gobierno como publicista de estos mercados. Se trata de desregular algunos sectores para que pueda ingresar la gente local. Los viajes en taxi pueden ser un ejemplo. Y esos beneficios deberían acarrear determinadas obligaciones para los operadores, siendo la clave, claro, que los operadores paguen por todo, incluso por la interconexión con el sector público. Imaginen que los operadores ganen dinero generando un porcentaje del margen en cada transacción. Imaginen que hay un período de concesión definido en quizá 15 años en los que pueden quedarse con estos beneficios y operar con ellos. Imaginen que a los consorcios que pujan para operarlos se les dice que quien entre con el margen porcentual más bajo de cada transacción para financiar todo cerrará el trato. El gobierno entonces sale de la estructura que ahora queda en manos del consorcio. Ellos o bien desatarán un montón de oportunidades económicas y obtendrán un porcentaje de ganancia o bien todo estallará en mil pedazos y será un duro golpe para los accionistas. Esto no necesariamente debe impactar al contribuyente. Y no existirían restricciones mercados alternativos. Esta sería solo otra alternativa más entre millones de foros de Internet. Pero podría ser muy diferente, porque tener acceso a esas estructuras con respaldo estatal podría incentivar a estos consorcios a invertir seriamente en el servicio. Porque obtendrían un montón de pequeñas transacciones para empezar a recuperar dinero. Estamos hablando de sectores como peluquería a domicilio, alquiler de juguetes, trabajos agrícolas, alquiler de ropa e incluso reparto de comida a domicilio, servicios para turistas, atención domiciliaria. Sería un mundo de intercambios muy pequeños, pero muy bien informados, porque los mercados electrónicos nacionales entregarán datos. Esta es una persona local que analiza incursionar en el mercado del cuidado de niños. Y podrían tener que financiar investigación de antecedentes y capacitaciones si quisieran entrar en ese mercado. Tendrían que evaluar entrevistas con padres locales que quisieran un grupo de cuidadores de niños. ¿Vale la pena? ¿Deberían mirar otros sectores? ¿Deberían mudarse a otra parte del país donde faltaran cuidadores de niños? Este tipo de datos puede tornarse una rutina. Los inversores pueden usar estos datos. Y si hay una falta de cuidadores de niños en una parte del país y nadie puede pagar la investigación de antecedentes y la capacitación, puede pagarla un inversor y el sistema devolverle pequeñas sumas por el aumento de ingresos de los individuos durante quizá los siguientes dos años. Este es un mundo de capitalismo atomizado. Es el comercio pequeño, de las personas comunes, pero muy bien informado, seguro, conveniente, económico e inmediato. Algunas investigaciones sugieren que podría generar nueva actividad económica por unos 100 millones de libras al día en un país del tamaño del Reino Unido. ¿Les suena improbable? Eso decía mucha gente de las transacciones automáticas en los intercambios financieros hace 20 años. No subestimen el poder de transformación de los mercados verdaderamente modernos. Gracias. (Aplausos)